hello everyone
uh i'm sort of surprised because from
the backstage i only saw those you know
tables so i was really sort of surprised
to see it's already prepared
anyway it's nice to see you again this
year enjoy portland beautiful weather
and u.s in general
this stuff that i'm making today is sort
of special because for most of my time
all the talks that i was making
they were all about javascript react
native tools you know releases and the
general experience working with native
modules
today i'm here to talk a bit about
reasonable our experience building that
and basically to tell you what we've
been after for the past year
so before we begin just a quick
introduction
i'm mike and surprisingly i'm a software
developer using react in particular
um i'm on a react native team
doing releases work around that helping
with general might enhance and some work
around common line tools as well so
three years ago i founded callstack
which is a consultancy with a mission to
help developers like you
launch their products on every platform
at the same time
that's three of us at chain react right
now with anna and adam we have a move
upstairs you can hit us up for some nice
t-shirts if there are any left stickers
and just generally chat about react
native and if you got any questions
about reasonable
about my talk feel free to hit us up
there
so before we start let me ask you a
question how many of you have ever heard
or used reasonable
before
okay so there is quite a few
those who didn't raise your hands don't
worry we got a few introduction slides
to go through reasonable basics so that
we all know uh what that's all gonna be
more or less about
so reasonable is a statically typed
language that is based on
more or less 25 years of occamol
experience you know
and research around multi-platform
development
it has a very powerful type system built
in with type inference and so that means
that you don't have to write types
everywhere you're writing your code
sometimes the compiler will just infer
the types for you
and the other key design point of reason
that i'm really excited about
is that reasonable is familiar to
javascript developers
and
i was sort of i sort of experienced that
myself because i used to
like be i used to learn a camel at my
university and i almost failed the
subject because of like being unable to
write algorithms in a comment it was
just too hard for me so when i first
experienced reasonable i was really
excited because many things that i
couldn't understand otherwise became
easy to understand straight away
and obviously it has a very very
powerful build system that makes build
times very fast especially the
incremental builds are so fast that
sometimes you even you know you you
can't even notice the that it rebuild in
the meantime
and so um just a quick uh introduction
to the syntax itself this is how you can
define a type declaration for something
that you would call an object in
javascript this is a record in
reasonable and in this case it's a
person that has a name and a surname of
type string
then you define
create an instance of that record
in this case it's me with my name and my
last name
and for example here's how you can
create an arrow function that accepts
this person as a first argument and what
it does is it basically console logs the
name
and this is something very similar to
spread operator in javascript which is
basically creating another instance of
that person as you can see type is
missing here it's automatically inferred
for you and it's obviously person
so more or less this is very similar to
javascript i picked those examples on
purpose just to show it's not a whole
new experience for you obviously there
are different things because it's a
different language all in all but in
many cases you will find yourself
already at home
so let's talk about ffi in reason ml
which is a foreign function interface
so ffi is a mechanism by which one
program written in this case in
reasonable can call routines or make use
of services that were made in other
language
so in case of reason this is about
accessing javascript code
for something that we call a binding and
bindings are just type definitions made
around javascript code to allow you
access
through types and guarantee sort of
types of safety when you are dealing
with a java world
and the following example will
demonstrate how you can actually create
a type definition for a math security
function in javascript so what you do
at the beginning is that you create
external
function of name sqrt and this is how
you will be calling that function from
reasonable and then you basically call
it as a next line
next what you do is you have to define
type definitions so you have to actually
think about the api declaration of the
javascript function in this case mafia
security and think what would be the
most appropriate type definition in this
case it's a float and it returns float
because that's essentially how it works
and as a last step you use some bucket
script magic in this case you annotate
this function
letting the compiler know that you just
want to call a global function map.sqrt
with the values that were given from the
reasonable world
now i'm not going to be diving into
details how ffi works itself if you'd
like to learn more about that i strongly
recommend you to listen to jared
podcast from reason town
when i first started writing reasonable
i didn't understand ffa at all it was
like a magic for me
and after listening to this podcast i
immediately got a full understanding of
how it all works so it's the best
resource right now where you can learn
how ffi works
so the reason i brought ffi
was to actually um
was to actually think about what writing
bindings
for javascript libraries gives us
so writing bindings to existing
javascript libraries is great because it
gives us
an ability to take a step back and think
about api decisions that we made in the
past
and so you can think of it
how
would your library look like if there
was no previous experience no user base
and no legacy code to support
and that's great because that opens up
your mind and allows you to think big
like how the future api and future
versions of your library could look like
and so a great example of that is reason
react which is a bindings to react in
reason ml
they are just bindings
but if you look at it closely you will
realize it has a different philosophy in
a few places
including for example built in state
management
different lifecycle methods and as you
can see from this snippet functional
render
if you actually go ahead and check the
future of react that repository that has
proposals about future versions of react
you'll see that some of the features are
already available in reason are actually
pending proposal to be discussed
so
i'll try to mention some of those
differences as we go along
so all these things mentioned previously
all together bring a lot of exciting
improvements to the react native
ecosystem
so let me ask you this question what
would your ideal react native workflow
be like if there were no constraints and
no prior art to support just think about
it for a second
i'm sure that there are you know
there are things that you thought about
that are fundamentally different
from what we currently have in react
native
or what we say is the best practice in
react native
thinking about them without all the
javascript context
makes you come up with observations
you'd never had otherwise
if you are a full-time conference
attendant and if you go to many
conferences a year it's probably not the
first time someone like me stands in
front of you and is about to say that
reasonable is great and you should use
it right
like i myself can remember for example
ken wheeler from many talks around
reasonable pretty exciting
yet somehow native development with
reason
is still behind
when i was chatting with people around
the community
with maintainers of bs react native in
particular
they told me that there's maybe just a
bunch of people using react native in
reason
and that got me thinking
why is that what's so hard or what is
the problem that makes reason not that
popular in react native
so first i asked myself and i started re
i started thinking about my journey when
i first started using reason i didn't
finish it
i stopped somewhere in the middle you
know
figured there was just too many tools to
set up too many different things that i
didn't know about to get up and running
to build a very simple mobile experience
so a few months later i was encouraged
by my friend mateos that works with me
and he sort of encouraged me to give it
another go and by the way if you don't
know mateusz it's that guy who said on
twitter that we all be writing reason
that was obviously
overestimated but i think it's gonna
happen eventually
and so
the next time i passed through all the
steps
i did some reverse engineering i look at
the source code i dealt with missing
documentation and all that stuff i've
been there and once i started writing
apps with reason and react native i got
so excited that i decided to do
everything i can to make it exciting
experience for everyone else
and so just to give you an idea how the
getting started with react native and
reason looks like right now
it's the first step from github and by
the way sorry for a bunch of white
slides now but it's a copy paste from
github
you have to install some dependencies
you know chances are you already have
few of them so you go to next step you
create some files you configure them you
don't really know what they are doing
then you add some scripts to your
package json and more and more and more
and more and you're sort of done at the
end you know and chances are that after
two slides or three slides that i showed
you you sort of had no idea what you
were already doing and
just started copying pasting stuff all
over you know
and and don't get me wrong because all
those steps that i showed you are like
100 legit they are like reasonable you
should do them eventually problem is
when you are just starting
you really have no idea what they are so
it just feels weird to set them up
and unfortunately as soon as i got
started another problem that i had was
missing documentation
so
in other words
like
it's luck
in my particular case what i was doing i
was trying to investigate animated api
and how to use it
and so
animated api is very tricky i mean it's
very hard to understand at the very
beginning at least it was for me
and trying to understand that reason was
even harder
so one may say that reason are just like
react native and reason these are just
bindings so eventually the api is the
same so why don't i why couldn't i just
go straight to react native
documentation learn animate it and just
do the same steps
problem is
it's not the same and that's the biggest
problem because you don't know where the
difference is and that makes you stuck
all over the place because you don't
really know which api is different
so ended up reverse engineering files
like this which is an interface file in
reason and it's like a public
declaration of your api so if you have a
file that has hundreds of functions the
interface file is what defines what is
visible outside so what i had to do is i
had to reverse engineer every animated
function like this analyze the type
declaration and see how it's used how it
can how it can be called and then i
think myself how i can make the
animation happen
and it's very great approach again it's
very good that we have this stuff but we
are yet to build the documentation and
tools around that to make it more easy
to consume by beginners like me back in
a day
so that was certainly a big problem
but luckily enough in a recent community
is
is very special like i don't remember
being in a community that will answer
every single question that i had on
discord under like a minute
that's that's like if you have ever
asked questions on discord there you
will know what i'm what i'm talking
about and that helped me a lot
because you probably know this feeling
when you're trying out a new technology
you get stuck every
half an hour and you wait for an answer
for five hours it's like it's impossible
to code like this you get frustrated you
stop it you throw it away and and that's
what happened with me
when i first started using greezum
so this is very special about this
community very encouraging
it helps you a lot
problem is
there wasn't you know enough for me to
feel confident about reason like i can't
build my entire professional
experience at my work based on asking
people all over because once if they
don't answer i'll be just stuck
so i decided to change that
as i said at the beginning
at call stack we have this mission of
helping developers building bar apps on
many platforms and so
right now we are using react native
because we believe this is the best
technology for running our apps on many
platforms at the same time
and as a leading consultancy in that
space we keep challenging ourselves
every day what can we do better
to make our experience of cross-platform
development even better you know
so we see reason as a great opportunity
to improve
in few key areas where react native
might be struggling right now and at the
same time we have few ideas that we have
observed throughout past three years
building react native in production that
we believe could be very useful when
connected with reason
and as a last benefit since we are
working with clients that are actually
running react native we have this great
opportunity to promote reason we can
just encourage our clients to do it and
by that we can contribute to the overall
ecosystem and growth and adoption of
reasonable
and so we decided to change that and we
decided to come up
with an uber project
and we call it a rebuild
so rebuild is an umbrella for many
different projects around react native
and reason
once they are connected all together we
hope they will contribute to even better
development in those technologies it's a
result of
different ideas that we had and we
experimented with over the past few
months
so rebuild from the very beginning has a
very modular architecture
when we break it into pieces
revolt contains bindings to react native
so that code that makes it possible to
actually use react native apis
we have powerful and ready to use
navigation
we have a very easy project generator
that makes it easy to start and we have
a whole new cli system
and we already started adapting rebuild
at call stack
so that whatever we are open source to
you is all is tested and doesn't contain
a lot of issues
so that you don't get frustrated like we
did back in a day
so in principle
we wanted rebel to be as easy to get
started as possible
so let's take a look at the project
generator
so in fact the process of creating a new
app with rebuild is as easy as creating
any other react native app
just show you a bunch of like
screenshots from github showing many
steps
but this is no longer true
we decided to stick to the current flow
which is about running react native in
it
but by default when you run react native
in it what you get is a react native app
with flow
so we decided to use a hidden feature of
init that is called
a template generator
and we can use it to tell react native
in it to create a different react native
app than by default
so how many of you have heard of this
feature before
okay quite a few i know i know i know
i know probably why
but um
that's what i'm saying if you haven't
heard about it don't freak out
uh
in fact there are many hidden other
features in react native that you can
just find out by reverse engineering a
bunch of different
code paths anyway template generator is
there to allow this particular use case
so to start using it
we can set a template flag at the end of
our command
to tell it to use
that template
so what happens when you run a react
native in it
is to scaffold the new up it goes
through the existing uh predefined
boilerplate in this case by default we
have two of them we have the navigation
template and the hello world template
so the hello world template is the one
that you get by default when you edit
your app you get a blue background some
some welcome to react native experience
this is where it's defined and so it
works by just copying and pasting those
files to your source code and installing
dependencies
so that way you get an out of the box
experience automatically
and you know in order to use rival on
the other hand
you again have to run react native init
with the hello chain react for example
name but you have to pass template flag
and rebuild as the name of the template
and the generator will attempt to
install the react native template
rebuild which is again just a template
that contains the the the hello world
application with the steps that we did
for you automatically so you don't have
to think about all the different
configurations to set up you got
everything in place
the only step that you have to do
manually is that you have to go to your
package json and you have to modify
the scripts so that the running
experience is even easier for you
we are working on making that automated
as well
partially the reason react native init
didn't do all the things that we wanted
is that it's not popular and the reason
why it's not popular and you don't know
about it is that its scope of features
is very small
you can just copy and paste files so our
idea is to make it a first class feature
in react native
propose an rfc so that you can also use
it maybe even internally to scaffold
applications
and just to help you in general react
native development
so let's talk about bindings
rebuild is based on bs react native as i
said and it's all about exposing
bindings to react native in other words
it's just a wrapper around the
javascript apis
unfortunately that means that for now
running rebuild requires you to cr to
spawn actually two bundlers at the same
time one is the metro bundler that you
already know from react native and the
other one is the buccal script build
system that will basically convert
reasonable to javascript and make it
possible to be accessed
and the focus of the first iteration was
to make sure that all the apis and
components are exposed in as most
accurate fashion as possible
and so to make it possible we
implemented the missing parts and we
also ship documentation so that you can
get started very easily
and the documentation itself shows usage
of almost all components and apis in
reason so you don't have to get stuck
and think like how you can use them you
can just glance the examples that we did
for you and you will be pretty much set
up
and so the principle that we have we had
for rebuild version one was to
sort of we aim for revolution instead of
evolution instead of revolution
and so if you've been already using vs
react native or any other um
wrapper with uh written reason ml you
should be able to just migrate
automatically without any issues
but let's start with a why
i mean when asked about reason for
reason or in other words why would you
even care about what i'm talking to you
about today
and why would you like to introduce yet
another abstraction to make react native
development even more complicated
i'd like to
sort of do it by an example because code
is worth more than 1000 words
so how many of you haven't used animated
at all before please raise your hand
okay
that's that's good because i have a one
slide
that does a very short introduction
it's a very very verbose introduction so
chances are you may disagree with it to
some extent if you've been already using
animated
but animated module allows you to
express your animations in a declarative
way and it all starts with creating an
animated value which is a holder for
values that you're going to use for
animation and so as the first thing you
give it a numeric value in this case
it's a zero
then you define an animation
that is a function that will be changing
the animation value so that we know how
to change it for how long and what the
end value will be like
and at the end you start it
so now that we know where we are more or
less
don't worry the examples are not even
gonna be using a lot of specific
animated things
let's do a small exercise
i will show you a few snippets and your
task will be to guess whether it's a
correct code
or incorrect operation
so let's assume that all the examples
that i'll show you are like valid
javascript as far as syntax and that
there are no flow errors at all
so in the first example we are dealing
with two animated values
that we want to combine together okay so
we got a full animated value and bar
animated value and we want to add them
up together
do you know what's the output going to
be like what's the value gonna be like
of those two animated values added
together
yeah it's gonna be one right this is
simplified but eventually this is one
so another example
we got two vectors okay one is a vector
with one and one coordinates the other
one has zero and zero coordinates
do you know what the result of this
operation will be
will it be an object with one and one
when we summarize each property
could be right that sounds that sounds
sort of reasonable
problem is it's a string
essentially it's an object object object
object string
so turns out vectors are not supported
by animated operations like
interpolation
addition multiplication
and it's a really interesting
undocumented implementation detail that
you will find out just when you get this
bug in production
and so with revolt
this operation is not possible
as you can see we got type error saying
that the value xy cannot be an argument
to the add operation
so that's how we can prevent those
issues from happening
at an example of reason and its typing
system
another example also from animated mo
animated module is about having one
animated value and interpolating it to
create another animated value so
interpolation creates a new animated
value by mapping input values from one
animated volume to some other animated
values so long story short if we have
animated value that can have values
between 0 and 300 we are mapping that to
0 and 1.
and so we got this function we are
calling it
and does anyone know what the the output
will be
i'll give you a quick
tip
yep
it's going to be red screen
we have really handy information by stop
tracking function missing which probably
is not going to tell you anything as
long as you basically try doing divide
and conquer technique and you end up
just removing that snippet from your
code base
and so we probably already know this you
probably already get this
interpolated values cannot be animated
i mean it's obvious once you start doing
that but i guess the first time you were
doing animated will be like
what's going on like what's wrong here
and so if you look at rebuild this again
is a type error so your code will not
even compile this is a legal operation
and you got an error message saying that
you basically cannot interpolate
uh canon animate interpolated values and
this looks very damp when it's like line
below another but if you have a function
that receives animated value you don't
control what you're going to receive so
having a correct typing makes it sort of
easier to operate across module
boundaries and make sure issues like
that do not exist in production
so this is by far my most favorite
feature of reason and what really gets
me excited about it and what makes it
different from typescript flow and all
other typing systems available within
the javascript community is that when
you create a bindings to a module
you have this ability to think about the
api and maybe change it in some places
you can add some sugar you can add some
wrappers and you can make sure that
certain issues do not happen and that's
why we were able to get rid of those
animated typing issues by adding few
different kinds of animated values and
making sure certain operations are not
possible in between them
another important part of rebuild is its
default navigation system
it started a while ago as bindings to
react navigation but we soon observed
that there is way more than we can do to
make a performant navigation for
reasonable and for react native in
javascript as well
and so it has a couple of differences
from what you would normally expect from
a regular javascript navigation system
one is that it has a native performance
thanks to react native gesture handler
all the gestures that you're gonna use
within your app are running on a native
fret meaning that
none of your logic will ever make your
gesture
struggle anytime
another big feature is that it has a
fully declarative interface and so if
you look at the code snippet you don't
have any static configuration everything
is part of your render method so if you
ever had issues with changing the state
of your navigation based on life cycle
of your component say header button
changes when you press it like edit mode
this is no longer hard you just need to
use your state and in this example you
just have to return a appropriate icon
based on the state of your component
and it's also super easy to implement
or change or provide custom animations
they are also part of your render method
so it's as easy as defining for example
fade vertical as a part of a render
method to have a model-like experience
without any hacks
animation itself is an object that has
this beautiful type declaration that
looks a bit strange at first but what it
says it says that it contains a function
for cart and for header interpolators
looking at the example reveals that
function is just a function to use for
animating in this case we want to use
spring animation which mimics the ios
mechanics so that the animation looks
almost real
and then we got the interpolators like
in this case we want the slide from left
to right animation so we can use
the translatex property
and so the navigation itself is still
pretty much in progress
the features we implemented are working
for us but we are looking forward to
collaborating with you on that to make
it even more production ready so that it
works for your use cases as well
and so i got the last part which is i
guess the most exciting but i'm running
short of time so
i'm really sorry that i will have to you
know speed it up
but um yesterday or two days ago at
speaker's dinner gant said that if i'm
gonna need some time when something goes
wrong
i could tell him to buy me five minutes
so i'm gonna ask him you can sell me
actually five minutes you know
the other way i'm not sure if that's
possible
anyway
the last part of rebuild is the whole
new cli system and if you've been
following react native you know that i'm
always excited about command line tools
like this is the first react amsterdam
conference where me and alexia announced
rmpm which later became a react native
link
and we used react native link to avoid
this experience of linking all the stuff
everywhere
so that it's just as easy as running a
single command
and you can forget about all the native
stuff
but link was just the first step what we
wanted to achieve was a completely
standalone system for managing your
react native apps without touching
native code and so
we never actually finished that because
we got busy with other react native
stuff but we'd like to use reasonable as
an opportunity to do this approach once
again all over
and additionally we'd like to abstract
away native code
so that working with react native feels
like working with expo or create react
native app you still got all the code in
place but you don't have to deal with
any native code
and you know just to summarize it
this may all sound really crazy or
really weird and you may be wondering
why we are trying to divide community or
something
truth is we are not
we have this compatibility principle and
regardless of you loving reason or not
believing in it or not all the
ingredients all the four ingredients
maybe except for the bindings are gonna
be available for react native anyway so
even if you're not planning on using
reason you will still be able to benefit
from those features
and so all the bits and pieces that we
are working on are mit licensed and are
available on our github so we are more
than welcome to join us on that journey
and help us make this development a
better experience
this is our discord channel where we
offer free support to all our open
source libraries and
where we actually keep discussing the
future of react native and reason and we
would love to have you on board we'd
love to hear your experience working
with react working with native modules
in production and essentially everything
that you ever done in react native is of
our interest so please join this channel
or just let me know in the most
convenient way for you how we can help
you and how we can make together reason
and react development even better
experience thank you very much
you